well such as china for instance um
us kind of favored the
chiang kai-shek in china and they didn't
overly like the communist regime but
they didn't directly help them for
various reasons
on the other hand the ussr had favored
uh the communist
leader mal and supplied them with a lot
of help and eventually
they took over mainland china other
cases where we had that proxy so i was a
fairly
large proxy battle although they didn't
help much on this end
another one where there's direct more
direct involvement
cases in southeast asia vietnam for
instance proxy battles
countries in central america where
directly or indirectly each side is
helping out their favored
regime the cold war the hostilities can
exist in other forms although the cold
war
doesn't quite exist doesn't exist or
doesn't quite exist at least in the
format that exists today
there's still the legacy of it at the
very least or some historians might say
it's gone on into
a different form because the warsaw pact
no longer exists the ussr no longer
exists
we have the russian federation but the
russian federation isn't so friendly
with
the uh current nato allies and there's a
cold war
where there's espionage between the two
for instance and
in terms of attacks well there's the
electronic attacks for instance
other attacks they refer to as the
asymmetric warfare
asymmetric because now the russian
federation by itself
is by itself isn't nearly as powerful as
the ussr it's lost a lot of
it's uh it's it's it's um
it's states such as the uh uh kazakhstan
ukraine and so on other places so the
ussr itself has been broken up but it's
lost essentially
it's it's satellite states such as the
east germany
czechoslovakia and all the other
countries used to be communist countries
so they can't directly take on nato so
they call asymmetric warfare where the
ussr
has been accused of meddling essentially
in affairs in the west
such as the aforementioned uh that i
talked about the previous section notes
american um elections
so this is the cold war that started
at the least 1950s although one might
say even before that some
some and whether or not it's continued
directly continued
or indirectly it still exists in some
form
this cold war
you can see the cold war had its origins
obviously in world war
ii former allies um split into two camps
and the countries that they each
involved that were involved on this side
the countries that were taken over on
this side
became part of two different alliances
now with this cold war it does have a
direct effect on the internet so world
war ii had a indirect
effect on the cold war cold wars we'll
see has had a direct effect on the
internet
the cold war one way that the two sides
were
competing was the space race
now what we're talking about is before
humans were able to send
artificial satellites into space they
were both
competing on the ground to be dominant
in different ways
with standard weapons conventional
weapons as they referred to
non-nuclear type weapons um but also
um when when nuclear weapons became more
common for each
uh major power they were competing and
still competing
in terms of uh their nuclear weaponry
but in addition to that
they're also trying to be dominant in
the space now there's a few reasons
why they were trying to be dominant
partly it was the bragging rights the
first country i could send an artificial
satellite
into space there's a great propaganda
effect we
you don't believe in the propaganda
effect well look at the
um what they call the sputnik
i'm talking about the vaccine the split
neck i think they called sputnik 2.
the russian federation said quote they
came up with the first vaccine cure
treatment for covid of course the only
test on a few dozen people whereas
normally you test on
tens of thousands one of the reasons why
they pushed for that
is for the bragging rights we are the
first country
that came up with it that's what what
they say and that's the story to stick
to it
but obviously no one's uh no other
countries have
wide skill adopted it because they only
tested on a few dozen people for gossip
when you should be testing
with well the americans need 30 000
people for it to be
at minimum to be to be approved by their
fda so there's bragging rights of that
don't underestimate that there's still
some breaking rights talking about terms
of
technological advances covet
bragging and other benefits who's
getting the covet vaccine first
there's obviously other advantages for
that but sending the satellite in the
space besides just the propaganda and
bragging rights the morale
the perceived morale advantages if one
can
actually develop a mechanism for
launching a satellite in space to
basically break earth's gravity
then that is a major strategic advantage
because you have technology lance
launched something in orbit
now potentially it's um
it's possible to be able to launch
something say from us
ussr longer range missiles
so it also has military applications
and the direct i think i've definitely
mentioned this a little bit
the direct analogy is korea
north korea was another one of the proxy
fights between
um the korean conflict between the
warsaw pact and the
and nato but modern day north korea
they're frequently doing various things
depending on who you ask
trying to launch missiles or they just
say artificial satellites but even if
they're
truly just researching the ability to
launch artificial
probes into space if they have that
ability to launch artificial probes into
space
then that improves their ability to
launch missiles
that can i believe they can reach the
hawaiian islands
the u.s part of the u.s and possibly
alaska but
also reach different parts of
continental us and that's why it's so
um somewhat of so much concern to the
u.s
that a state like north korea is either
working under quote
satellite launching capability or
essentially the rocket program and other
states
in the middle east are of
have been of um of um
interest so we say to countries such as
the u.s for different
reasons but for similar essentially that
developing that technology
so in the 1950s
it appeared that the ussr now this isn't
a quote technological ad but a real one
they had the technological edge what was
happening was in 1957 the americans
the americans if you look at their mail
you've heard probably many things about
their military spending budget
um one metric they use is the number of
aircraft carriers the the ships that can
carry air
uh full fleet carriers that can carry
airplanes jets bombers
uh dead bombish type type planes
um they have a fleet of 20 of these last
i checked
um china just got one a secondhand one
that was a cast off from the old ussr
um the ussr i'm not too sure how many uh
sorry the
russian federation how many they have
but they don't have that 20. and canada
fleet carriers has zero so they they
this is one reason why they spend
uh their military budget so much another
reason is
to use a programming metaphor they if i
described how they spent on their weapon
tree
using a metaphor programming metaphor
well
they would be writing a program that had
all the bells and whistles
handled all the cases or almost all the
cases that you can imagine
had fancy features for robustness and so
on
their artificial satellite 1950s a
sophisticated one
bells and whistles three stage rockets
so you'd launch off the one stage
enough of a a rocket to launch you so
the initial part would
fall off we didn't need any more because
we were uh we were up high enough we
had uh earth's gravity was loaded up so
we had a second stage and so on that's
what pages rockets very simply put
and they had planned it as the first
artificial satellite
to be sent into space however the ussr
beat them to the punch
they essentially their metaphor to
extend the metaphor of programming they
the u.s planned a very fancy program a
very fancy
uh they included very fancy technology
in the rocket
what'd the soviets do ah essentially
and they really surprised the whole
world basically with their hack they
launched sputnik one
the the latest footnick i think it's to
anyhow the i know it's sputnik something
the
so-called vaccine for kovid that was
supposed to be developed by the
and you can hear my and other peoples
people who are experts in the field
have some skepticism about the the the
efficacy of it
um but not the efficacy of the the
sputnik one
efficacy of the vaccine split neck one
basically
it was just an adaptation of their
military rockets
and it was the first artificial
satellite and we see the sputnik
here in a picture so it's brought into
orbit
using adaptation of their military
technology
well let's put this in perspective
now besides having this cold war at the
time
nuclear weapons were new in 1945 they
were first
and the only time that they're used
against nation state was against japan
and hiroshima and nagasaki
new and very scary weapon and there's
still a scary weapon although not so new
in the 1950s if you look at old history
books
history documentaries there was very
much a fear
of
the possibility of nuclear war nuclear
annihilation
um they used to refer to it as mad
mutually-ish i believe was mad mutually
assured destruction
where both sides would wipe each other
out if a nuclear war occurred
so both sides were quite scared
consequently with this
background information the u.s
did not take this well it wasn't
it wasn't similar to the reception when
the russian federation said that we have
a cure for covet they just
they didn't react much most countries
didn't react much they tried to analyze
what information was available for the
the um vaccine coveted but the satellite
culvert
basically caused the americans to freak
right out
because for the reasons i described well
there's the
the the morale boost there's the
propaganda bragging rights but also
militarily
if the ussr could launch an artificial
satellite
now they've got believed in advance
quite rightfully
that they have advanced their missile
technology
to better attack the us and its allies
so in response the u.s created
arpa the arpa project which is yet
another acronym
the advanced research projects agency in
the u.s
and this agency still exists today uh
it's undergone number of name changes
you look under arpa i believe that's
back to darpa again arpa darpa and then
uh you can look it up i've lost track of
the number of name changes
it still exists and you can actually see
the research that they do they're not
just involved in research for military
research
but actually saw uh under the current
uh current project name they actually
are conducting research
they have early on in the spring they're
conducting research for a cohort vaccine
they do some good work um so but the
motivations for our book came from
the launch of the sputnik which came
from
the cold war which came which was
indirectly affected by
world war ii but we still haven't gotten
to the internet yet the internet's
coming up
we're building to the climax here
just to add insult to entry to make the
us feel like well no they're actually
trying to advance their search
legitimately later at night so the early
1950s earlier in 1957
the ussr launched sputnik later in 1957
they launched yet another artificial
life
an artificial satellite that could carry
a life form up in it
and that's different because sputnik
didn't actually have any life forms it
didn't have to have a life support
system
now they developed a second satellite
that could have an artificial
uh that had a life support system that
launched a dog leica
which is supposed to be russian forgive
me if i'm pronouncing that i'm
undoubtedly pronouncing this wrong for
russian speaking people as best i can
leica uh which referred to barker barker
and russian
therefore to you poor poor little guy
it's a one-way trip to space
yeah and that's not a sarcastic sigh i
yeah double checking my technology as
far as i see
i just took a quick look at my recording
one that's why there's a bit of a break
there
to see if it's still appears recording
thank gosh
okay
before this the us had the image
basically as being
the numeral uno and that wasn't just
propaganda
they were the first ones that actually
successfully
developed and actually
used nuclear weaponry
and that's a scary thing good thing or
not
well good u.s thought it was a good
thing in terms of their
their defense obviously not so good for
the country where it was dropped on them
but this really cemented the image of us
being dominant
and in terms of conventional forces they
were
extremely powerful if you interested you
could actually look at the comparisons
of the u.s weapons at the end of world
war ii
their fighter craft their warships
and you compare their theirs versus
their tanks versus soviet
and typically they come out ahead um in
terms of one-on-one but the total
numbers
uh so that the the soviet union could do
this
it really shook um that image
and as i've said if they could lance
launch these artificial satellites and
space as i said many times
then that improves their ability to hit
continental u.s
so as a solution quote solution
it was believed the solution was well
let's throw more money in math and
science
and we saw with the uh was it the von
neumann interview if you actually saw
the extra little one
the it was believed that in grade school
that they needed more math and science
uh
especially high school so that americans
coming out of grade school
because not so many americans then not
so many people in the world
actually got a post-secondary education
could
produce better work out think their
soviet counterparts and then some of the
interesting things i dug up
trying to find specific now we've heard
out of that if you've watched your
news reels or propaganda reels actual
newsreels
on that era they frequently say do this
and they'd say do
x action do it for your country buy
bonds do it for your country
it's patriotic and they still do that
sort of thing these days
um for a while the
the current american president said i
believe he said i know the
incoming president said um wear a mask
it's it's it's your your american duty
something that effect
now fine now this is the first time i've
heard someone say apparently
this very pitch for your own sake but
for patriotism
do your homework apparently that was a
quote from the harvard university
president at the time james bryant
so it was believed to be studying was
patriotic
now whether or not it succeeded getting
kids to
do their math homework well that that's
another thing
dwight eisenhower white oops white
eisenhower i talked about
in terms of we call the american
election eisenhower
versus uh stevenson he was a famous
american general and as you know he
became